<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>My page | OptiML PSE</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/</link><atom:link href="https://optimalpse.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>My page</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://optimalpse.github.io/media/icon_hu5a76b0abcb7258b41069941c74c2d861_196285_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>My page</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/</link></image><item><title>Example Event</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/event/example/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2030 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/event/example/</guid><description>&lt;p>Slides can be added in a few ways:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Create&lt;/strong> slides using Wowchemy&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://wowchemy.com/docs/managing-content/#create-slides" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;em>Slides&lt;/em>&lt;/a> feature and link using &lt;code>slides&lt;/code> parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Upload&lt;/strong> an existing slide deck to &lt;code>static/&lt;/code> and link using &lt;code>url_slides&lt;/code> parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Embed&lt;/strong> your slides (e.g. Google Slides) or presentation video on this page using &lt;a href="https://wowchemy.com/docs/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shortcodes&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Further event details, including page elements such as image galleries, can be added to the body of this page.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Learning Resources</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/learning-resources/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/learning-resources/</guid><description>&lt;div class="container">
&lt;p>Here we outline some recommended material for students wishing to start on topics related to optimisation, artificial intelligence and dynamic systems from the process systems perspective.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="table-of-contents">Table of Contents&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#optimization">Optimization&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#reinforcement-learning">Reinforcement Learning&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#applied-statistics">Applied Statistics&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#dynamic-optimization-optimal-control-and-mpc">Dynamic Optimization (Optimal control) and MPC&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#linear-algebra">Linear Algebra&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#machine-learning">Machine Learning&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#prerequisites">Prerequisites&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#remarks">Remarks&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;div class="two-column">
&lt;div class="topic-box">
&lt;h2 id="optimization">Optimization&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="books">Books&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Numerical Optimization&lt;/strong> by J. Nocedal and S. Wright
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Great book to learn continuous optimization algorithms, the suggestion it to implementing pseudo-codes in your language of choice as you traverse through the book.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Nonlinear and Mixed-Integer Optimization: Fundamentals and Applications&lt;/strong> by C. A. Floudas
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A favorite source to learn convex mixed-integer optimization.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Algorithms for Optimization&lt;/strong> by Mykel J. Kochenderfer and Tim A. Wheeler
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A comprehensive introduction to optimization, focus is on algorithm implementation rather than theoretical background, includes algorithms written in Julia.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="online-courses">Online Courses&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Convex Optimization I&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Convex Optimization II&lt;/strong> by S. Boyd
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Great content all over! Lectures 13-19 of COI and all COII are great, and generally underrated. An online book is also available.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Discrete Optimization&lt;/strong> by P. Van Hentenryck and C. Coffrin from Coursera learning platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Interactive and very fun course to learn discrete optimization.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Deterministic Optimization&lt;/strong> by S. Ahmed from edX learning platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A great interactive course which gives an overview to many optimization instances and problems, also accompanied with practical material.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="topic-box">
&lt;h2 id="reinforcement-learning">Reinforcement Learning&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="books-1">Books&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Reinforcement Learning: An Introduction&lt;/strong> by R. S. Sutton and A. G. Barto
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>One of the most complete books on the subject, latest version is from 2018. Complements nicely with online courses. Freely available online.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Reinforcement Learning Specialization by Martha White and Adam White from Coursera covers a significant part of this book.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="online-courses-1">Online Courses&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Deep Reinforcement Learning&lt;/strong> by Sergey Levine at UC Berkeley
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Great content, including YouTube videos, homework, a subreddit, GitHub repositories, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Reinforcement Learning&lt;/strong> by David Silver
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Nice and easy material to understand.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Reinforcement Learning Specialization&lt;/strong> by Martha White and Adam White from Coursera learning platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The course is mostly based on the book &amp;ldquo;Reinforcement Learning: An Introduction&amp;rdquo; by Sutton and Barto, making it a more interactive way to go through the book if that suits your learning style.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Reinforcement Learning&lt;/strong> by Emma Brunskill at Stanford
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>All videos and assignments are available, YouTube list &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLuBib0ZpH85femD3SC8mEK84sBbGEPX8l" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Practical Reinforcement Learning&lt;/strong> by P. Shvechikov and A. Panin from Coursera learning platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Good overall content and intuitive explanations, includes online quizzes and exercises.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="topic-box">
&lt;h2 id="applied-statistics">Applied Statistics&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="books-2">Books&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Information Theory, Inference, and Learning Algorithms&lt;/strong> by David MacKay
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Great all-round book, conceptually clear and at the same time practical when it comes to algorithms. It is great for beginners but also useful for practitioners.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Online lectures based on the book also available &lt;a href="https://www.inference.org.uk/mackay/itila/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a> or on &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLruBu5BI5n4aFpG32iS0E_g4lTMkKRYGa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">YouTube&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The book is freely available &lt;a href="https://www.inference.org.uk/itila/book.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="online-courses-2">Online Courses&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Bayesian Statistics: From Concept to Data Analysis&lt;/strong> by Herbert Lee from Coursera learning platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A great introduction to Bayesian thinking.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Bayesian Statistics: Techniques and Models&lt;/strong> by Matthew Heiner from Coursera learning platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A continuation from the above course.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Bayesian Methods for Machine Learning&lt;/strong> by D. Polykovskiy and Al. Novikov
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Nice practical examples and intuitive explanations on ML algorithms based on Bayesian thinking. Includes topics such as Variational Autoencoder, Gaussian processes &amp;amp; Bayesian optimization.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Information Theory, Pattern Recognition, and Neural Networks&lt;/strong> by David MacKay
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Great source to learn information theory, very intuitive and clear explanations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Based on a freely available &lt;a href="https://www.inference.org.uk/mackay/itprnn/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">book&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="topic-box">
&lt;h2 id="dynamic-optimization-optimal-control-and-mpc">Dynamic Optimization (Optimal control) and MPC&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="books-3">Books&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dynamic Programming and Optimal Control&lt;/strong> by D. P. Bertsekas
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Nice presentation that shows the relations between Dynamic Programming and Optimal Control. Written from a computer science perspective.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Predictive Control: With Constraints&lt;/strong> by J. Maciejowski
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Good introductory material to Model Predictive Control.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Numerical Optimal Control&lt;/strong> by M. Diehl and S. Gros
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Great source on how to solve OC problems numerically, goes very well with his online course.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Nonlinear and Dynamic Optimization: From Theory to Practice&lt;/strong> by B. Chachuat
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>This is a great source for a formal and complete description of dynamic optimization problems in engineering practice. It might be slightly more mathematically demanding than the three previous sources.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Model Predictive Control: Theory, Computation, and Design&lt;/strong> by J. B. Rawlings, D. Q. Mayne and M. M. Diehl
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Probably the most complete book on linear MPC, although it might be a difficult read for a beginner in the topic.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="online-courses-3">Online Courses&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Numerical Optimal Control&lt;/strong> by M. Diehl
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Very complete learning material, goes very well with his book.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Underactuated Robotics&lt;/strong> by R. Tedrake, R. Deits and T. Koolen from edX learning platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A nice course which covers topics on Dynamic Programming, Control and Dynamic Optimization (can also be found &lt;a href="http://underactuated.mit.edu/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Nptel&lt;/strong> by the Indian Institutes of Technology (IIT) and Indian Institute of Science (IISc)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>There are great courses on this site, however, those on Control, State Estimation, Model Predictive Control, and Optimal Control seem particularly good.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="topic-box">
&lt;h2 id="linear-algebra">Linear Algebra&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="books-4">Books&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Introduction to Linear Algebra&lt;/strong> by G. Strang
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Great presentation and intuition on the topic, goes well with his online video lectures.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Linear Algebra&lt;/strong> by Jim Hefferon
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Freely available online, very enjoyable exercises.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="online-courses-4">Online Courses&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Linear Algebra - Foundations to Frontiers&lt;/strong> by M. Myers and R. van de Geijn from edX learning platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Great course, gives mathematical background as well as great practical exercises.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Linear Algebra&lt;/strong> by G. Strang
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Similar to his book, Linear Algebra is presented in a very intuitive and easy to understand fashion.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="topic-box">
&lt;h2 id="machine-learning">Machine Learning&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="books-5">Books&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Deep Learning&lt;/strong> by I. Goodfellow, Y. Bengio and A. Courville
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Authored by pioneers on the field, freely available. Probably the best book on Deep Learning.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn and TensorFlow&lt;/strong> by A. Geron
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>For people who want to learn ML by doing practical examples.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="online-courses-5">Online Courses&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Deep Learning Specialization&lt;/strong> by Andrew Ng, K. Katanforoosh and B. Mourri from Coursera learning platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A series of 5 courses, that take you from knowing nothing to a very good understanding and practical training on deep learning. Explanations need a minimum mathematical requirement.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Machine Learning&lt;/strong> by Andrew Ng
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The course that made Andrew Ng famous. A very nice course, although might be slightly outdated. You can also find his course at Stanford &lt;a href="https://see.stanford.edu/Course/CS229" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="topic-box">
&lt;h2 id="prerequisites">Prerequisites&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This section outlines useful material that can help polish your math and programming skills before (or while) you are learning optimization and/or machine learning.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Linear Algebra&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Although there is a whole section about linear algebra, I thought I should emphasize it, as it is one of the pillars for both optimization and machine learning.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Python programming&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>There is a HUGE number of python courses, and even a significant number of online posts ranking the different courses, so a little google search might be the best way to find the best course for you.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A course I am confident recommending is &lt;a href="https://www.edx.org/course/introduction-to-computer-science-and-programming-using-python" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Introduction to Computer Science and Programming Using Python&lt;/a> by MIT on the edX learning platform. Very complete course, although it is quite time consuming.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mathematics for Machine Learning&lt;/strong> by Imperial College London
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A three course specialization, focusing on linear algebra, multivariate calculus, and principal component analysis.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Book freely available &lt;a href="https://mml-book.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Algorithms Specialization&lt;/strong> by Tim Roughgarden from Stanford at the Coursera platform
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A very nice course that teaches the fundamentals of the design and analysis of algorithms. Focuses particularly on the practical aspects, but also gives some theory, and makes thinking algorithmically quite fun.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div class="topic-box">
&lt;h2 id="remarks">Remarks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Note that blogs, GitHub repositories, YouTube symposiums, online classes and tutorials can be excellent learning material. Particularly for ML, RL and DL there are new courses and tutorials coming out every day! Maybe worthwhile exploring the web on your own :).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can have a look at our codes section for some code-tutorials developed by the group, or to our additional resources section, where we list some podcasts, blogs, and other sites that might be of interest.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Automated Knowledge Discovery</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/automated-knowledge-discovery/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/automated-knowledge-discovery/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Automated knowledge discovery streamlines the process of identifying meaningful mathematical models from experimental data. By employing algorithms that can recognise patterns and derive equations, this approach facilitates the creation of predictive and interpretable models for chemical reactions. This is particularly important in fields like reaction engineering, where understanding the dynamics of chemical systems is crucial for process design, optimisation and control. Automated knowledge discovery methods not only speed up the discovery of kinetic models but also enhances our understanding of complex chemical processes through symbolic models, making them a powerful tool in chemical process development.
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://pubs.rsc.org/en/content/articlelanding/2024/dd/d3dd00212h" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Link to publication.&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data-driven Distributionally Robust MPC</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/ddd-robust-mpc/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/ddd-robust-mpc/</guid><description>&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/post/ddd-robust-mpc/featured_huc143c5fbe1bce1fb288127d116a2ff26_188351_a18c929632be9337a2b49c7ef61eb491.webp 400w,
/post/ddd-robust-mpc/featured_huc143c5fbe1bce1fb288127d116a2ff26_188351_495bb553de414ddb953638cc428da150.webp 760w,
/post/ddd-robust-mpc/featured_huc143c5fbe1bce1fb288127d116a2ff26_188351_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://optimalpse.github.io/post/ddd-robust-mpc/featured_huc143c5fbe1bce1fb288127d116a2ff26_188351_a18c929632be9337a2b49c7ef61eb491.webp"
width="760"
height="420"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/th>
&lt;th>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/post/ddd-robust-mpc/fig2_hue3a80ef0b711c4daa77d7e00e1f5ca5b_48538_b7ebf461d1f0b4c131ae742cc2d2ad41.webp 400w,
/post/ddd-robust-mpc/fig2_hue3a80ef0b711c4daa77d7e00e1f5ca5b_48538_99493893c1bc6d199e0dc6da5ca61393.webp 760w,
/post/ddd-robust-mpc/fig2_hue3a80ef0b711c4daa77d7e00e1f5ca5b_48538_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://optimalpse.github.io/post/ddd-robust-mpc/fig2_hue3a80ef0b711c4daa77d7e00e1f5ca5b_48538_b7ebf461d1f0b4c131ae742cc2d2ad41.webp"
width="760"
height="196"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;/table>
&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Data-driven distributionally robust MPC (DRMPC) is an optimal control scheme, which - instead of considering only one distribution as in SMPC - determines control actions with respect to the worst-case distribution from a set of distributions (the set is known as ambiguity set). The research mainly focuses on:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Exact reformulations of underlying distributionally robust optimisation problems for the purpose of computational efficiency.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Proofs of stability and convergence.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Propagation of ambiguity sets in dynamical systems.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2023/26516" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nonlinear Wasserstein Distributionally Robust Optimal Control&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0098135422004458" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tube-based distributionally robust model predictive control for nonlinear process systems via linearization&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data-Driven Optimization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/ddo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/ddo/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Many engineering optimization problems can be described as "costly" black box problems, where the number of function evaluations is constrained. Engineers often create precise models of physical systems that are either differentiable or inexpensive to evaluate. These models can be solved efficiently, and their solutions can be applied to the actual system. However, when gradient information or cost-effective models are not available, it becomes necessary to use efficient optimization methods that rely solely on function evaluations - "data". These data-driven optimization algorithms are tailored to optimize functions without relying on explicit derivative information. The methods generally fall into two primary categories: model-based derivative-free methods, also referred to as surrogate-based optimization, and direct derivative-free methods. Model-based methods use information obtained through sampling the objective function to build, consult and update a model of the objective function during optimization. Direct methods navigate the optimization process based on sampled information only. Situated in-between these two categories are the finite-difference methods, which approximate derivatives using function evaluations.
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Data-driven Optimization for Enterprise-Wide Optimization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/ddo-enterprise/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/ddo-enterprise/</guid><description>&lt;img src="trajectory_DDC_400_high_ESCAPE_r.svg" alt="A simple SVG graphic"/>
&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Traditionally, optimization of chemical engineering systems relies on gradients of model expressions. Depending on the effort required to develop accurate models, it might be more efficient to jump the model-building step. Instead, we can use derivative-free optimization (DFO) - also known as black-box or 'data-driven' optimization - for optimal controller tuning, reactor design, experiment design, or flowsheet design based purely on input-output evaluations. This would for example involve the use of Bayesian optimization or trust region methods to iteratively construct and optimize surrogates of the system's input-output evaluations. Rather than use black-box optimization to optimize physical systems or simulations, we can solve complex coordination problems where the black-box evaluations involve optimization problems themselves. The holy grail of process systems operations would be to integrate all decision-making units that arise in the interaction between supply chain players and their hierarchical levels of decision-making. To this end, we can use DFO to determine the coordinating 'complicating' variables in value chain and multi-level hierarchical planning-scheduling-control problems, otherwise determined by heuristics, decomposition techniques, or distributed optimization.
&lt;/div>
&lt;h4 id="related-publications">Related Publications:&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>[1] D. van de Berg, T. Savage, P. Petsagkourakis, D. Zhang, N. Shah, E. A. del Rio-Chanona, 2022,&amp;ldquo;Data-driven optimization for process systems engineering applications,&amp;rdquo; Chemical Engineering Science, 248, 117135.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] D. van de Berg, P. Petsagkourakis, N. Shah, E. A. del Rio-Chanona, 2023a, &amp;ldquo;Data-driven coordination of subproblems in enterprise-wide optimization under organizational considerations,&amp;rdquo; AIChE Journal, 69(4), e17977.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[3] D. van de Berg, N. Shah, E. A. del Rio-Chanona, 2023b, &amp;ldquo;Hierarchical planning-scheduling-control – Optimality surrogates and derivative-free optimization,&amp;rdquo; arXiv:2310.07870&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Digital Twinning for Bioprocesses - from Hybrid to Data-Driven Models</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/dt-bioprocesses/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/dt-bioprocesses/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
My work focus on machine learning applications in surrogate modelling, time series prediction, and reinforcement learning process modelling, scheduling, and optimization of bioengineering, has resulted in a unique framework combining kinetic modelling and machine learning for optimizing dynamic systems. At the same time, we apply a novel offline RL framework for optimal bioprocess production scheduling. In contrast to the traditional RL algorithms like temporal difference (TD) learning, we utilise the transformer model to treat the sequential decision-making process through sequential modelling.
&lt;/div>
&lt;h4 id="related-publications">Related Publications&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>[1] Zhang, D., &amp;amp; del Río Chanona, E. A. (Eds.). (2023). &lt;em>Machine Learning and Hybrid Modelling for Reaction Engineering: Theory and Applications&lt;/em>. Royal Society of Chemistry. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1039/9781837670178" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1039/9781837670178&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] Wang, H., Kontoravdi, C., del Rio Chanona, E. A. (2023). A Hybrid Modelling Framework for Dynamic Modelling of Bioprocesses. In A. C. Kokossis, M. C. Georgiadis, &amp;amp; E. Pistikopoulos (Eds.), &lt;em>Computer Aided Chemical Engineering&lt;/em> (Vol. 52, pp. 469-474). Elsevier. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-443-15274-0.50075-5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-443-15274-0.50075-5&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Enhancing Process Performance - Adversarially Robust Real-Time Optimization and Control</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/adversarially-robust-rto/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/adversarially-robust-rto/</guid><description>&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/post/adversarially-robust-rto/featured_hu63da2c1af1c376b8fb2aa052842c3fe5_291394_b49de48b398d2c7f55adad04ae650a02.webp 400w,
/post/adversarially-robust-rto/featured_hu63da2c1af1c376b8fb2aa052842c3fe5_291394_c97b6abcdc88533565a4ed2ad3174753.webp 760w,
/post/adversarially-robust-rto/featured_hu63da2c1af1c376b8fb2aa052842c3fe5_291394_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://optimalpse.github.io/post/adversarially-robust-rto/featured_hu63da2c1af1c376b8fb2aa052842c3fe5_291394_b49de48b398d2c7f55adad04ae650a02.webp"
width="760"
height="538"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/th>
&lt;th>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/post/adversarially-robust-rto/Fig1b_hu447be7f63e7709d5877a7cd7a506c71e_486799_3ba996b7e5830e912eaf4021c8d3338a.webp 400w,
/post/adversarially-robust-rto/Fig1b_hu447be7f63e7709d5877a7cd7a506c71e_486799_29b5365abb3bbdfdcbbb6ade8e58a75e.webp 760w,
/post/adversarially-robust-rto/Fig1b_hu447be7f63e7709d5877a7cd7a506c71e_486799_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://optimalpse.github.io/post/adversarially-robust-rto/Fig1b_hu447be7f63e7709d5877a7cd7a506c71e_486799_3ba996b7e5830e912eaf4021c8d3338a.webp"
width="760"
height="515"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;/table>
&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Real-Time Optimization (RTO) plays a crucial role in the process operation hierarchy by determining optimal set-points for the lower-level controllers. However, at the control layer, these set-points may be difficult to track due to challenges in implementation as a result of disturbances, measurement noise, and actuator performance limitations. To address this, we introduced the Adversarially Robust Real-Time Optimization and Control (ARRTOC) algorithm. ARRTOC addresses this issue by finding set-points which are both optimal and inherently robust to implementation errors at the control layers. ARRTOC draws inspiration from adversarial machine learning, offering a novel constrained Adversarially Robust Optimization solution applied to the RTO layer. By integrating controller design with RTO, ARRTOC enhances overall system performance and robustness by ensuring the chosen set-points are tailored to the underlying controller designs. This concept is best illustrated visually as per the attached figures, where the performance of a controller around two possible set-points is compared: the global optimum (scenario 1 in blue) and the adversarially robust optimum (scenario 2 in red). We observe that, paradoxically, operating at the adversarially robust optimum yields a 30% larger mean objective value compared to operating at the global optimum due to its inherent robustness.
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.04386" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Link to publication.&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Human-in-the-Loop Bayesian Optimization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/human-in-the-loop-bo/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/human-in-the-loop-bo/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Bayesian optimisation has been successfully applied in a number of complex domains including engineering systems where derivatives are often not available, such as those that involve simulation or propriety software. By removing the human from decision-making processes in favour of maximising statistical quantities such as expected improvement, complex functions can be optimised in an efficient number of samples. However, these engineering systems are often engaged with by domain experts such as engineers or chemists, and as such the behaviour of the underlying function cannot be considered completely unknown a-priori. Therefore, there exists significant scope to take advantage of the benefits of Bayesian optimisation in optimising expensive derivative-free problems, whilst enabling domain experts to inform the decision-making process, putting the human back into the loop.
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02852" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Link to publication.&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Machine-Assisted Synthesis Planning</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/</guid><description>&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/featured_hu1277959bc9d8bf7b63da181e7deac72f_132501_99c49ce06eca76d1645cc0026950f741.webp 400w,
/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/featured_hu1277959bc9d8bf7b63da181e7deac72f_132501_8277307cf727e0a694ff46a47c1960cc.webp 760w,
/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/featured_hu1277959bc9d8bf7b63da181e7deac72f_132501_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://optimalpse.github.io/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/featured_hu1277959bc9d8bf7b63da181e7deac72f_132501_99c49ce06eca76d1645cc0026950f741.webp"
width="760"
height="366"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/th>
&lt;th>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/single_step_models_hu99e0fc5d598cd5acbee322e571484c6a_781673_a4fe2cea10d02aa22f03f7a0660a311c.webp 400w,
/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/single_step_models_hu99e0fc5d598cd5acbee322e571484c6a_781673_1492e523799c85c66126e483fd1854de.webp 760w,
/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/single_step_models_hu99e0fc5d598cd5acbee322e571484c6a_781673_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://optimalpse.github.io/post/machine-assisted-synthesis/single_step_models_hu99e0fc5d598cd5acbee322e571484c6a_781673_a4fe2cea10d02aa22f03f7a0660a311c.webp"
width="760"
height="555"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;/table>
&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Synthesizing organic molecules in a sustainable way is a decisive factor towards accelerated drug discovery. Finding synthesis pathways from potential reactants towards the molecule or product of interest is challenging. Traditionally, expert chemists use their own intuition to find potential disconnection sites in the product molecule to arrive at one or more reactant intermediates. These intermediates are subject to further inspection to finally arrive at reactants (building blocks) that can be purchased off-shelf. The iterative process from the molecular product to building blocks is formally known as retrosynthesis. To aid scientists in this endeavor, researchers have proposed a variety of computational tools based on heuristics, reaction rules, or data-driven approaches. Within recent years, machine learning (ML) has received tremendous attention for retrosynthesis. While ML algorithms are seen to be successful at proposing viable synthesis routes towards simpler molecules, there are many remaining challenges until these techniques will have a significant impact on molecular synthesis and discovery. The interested reader is referred to the references below.
&lt;/div>
&lt;h4 id="related-publications">Related Publications&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>[1] Hastedt F, Bailey RM, Hellgardt K, Yaliraki SN, del Rio Chanona EA, Zhang D. Investigating the Reliability and Interpretability of Machine Learning Frameworks for Chemical Retrosynthesis. ChemRxiv. 2024; doi:10.26434/chemrxiv-2024-qdgnv-v3&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] Segler, M., Preuss, M. &amp;amp; Waller, M. Planning chemical syntheses with deep neural networks and symbolic AI. Nature 555, 604–610 (2018). &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature25978" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1038/nature25978&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[3] Connor W. Coley et al., A robotic platform for flow synthesis of organic compounds informed by AI planning.Science365,eaax1566(2019) DOI:10.1126/science.aax1566&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[4] Tu, Z., Stuyver, T., &amp;amp; Coley, C. (2023). Predictive chemistry: machine learning for reaction deployment, reaction development, and reaction discovery. Chemical Science, 14(2), 226–244.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Multi Agent Reinforcement Learning for Supply Chain Optimisation</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/marl-sc/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/marl-sc/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning (MARL) has emerged as a powerful approach to tackle complex decision-making problems involving multiple interacting agents. In the context of supply chain optimization, MARL enables agents to learn and adapt their strategies in a decentralised manner, leading to more efficient and resilient supply chain operations. Unlike traditional centralized optimization methods, MARL allows for the consideration of local objectives and constraints of individual agents, leading to more realistic and effective solutions in dynamic and uncertain environments. In the chemical sector, supply chain optimisation is important due to the inherent complexities and risks associated with handling and transporting hazardous materials. MARL can be particularly beneficial in this context by enabling agents, such as suppliers, manufacturers, and distributors, to coordinate and optimize their operations collaboratively. This can lead to improved inventory management, reduced costs, and enhanced safety and compliance measures, ultimately contributing to more sustainable and competitive chemical supply chains. Thus, the application of MARL in supply chain optimisation holds significant promise for driving innovation and efficiency in the chemical industry.
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Optimizing Membrane-Based CO2 Capture Technologies for Industrial Applications</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/co2-capture-membrane/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/co2-capture-membrane/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Industrial processes, particularly power generation plants, cement and steel production factories are major contributors to carbon emissions. Developing effective CO2 capture technologies is crucial for achieving net-zero emissions and mitigating climate change. Membrane-based capture technologies offer a promising approach for separating CO2 from flue gas. Membrane-based capture offers several advantages, including lower footprint, easier scalability, and potentially lower energy requirements compared to other methods. By optimizing these systems through mathematical models, we can unlock the full potential of these processes analyzing different alternatives of design and operation.
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Related Publications:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[1] Ana M. Arias, Nicolás J. Scenna, Patricia L. Mores, 2023. Membrane superstructure optimization for carbon capture from cement plants. Water content influence on optimal solution, Int. J. Greenh. Gas Control 129. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijggc.2023.103964" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijggc.2023.103964&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] Mores, P.L., Arias, A.M., Scenna, N.J., Mussati, M.C., Mussati, S.F., 2019. Cost-based comparison of multi-stage membrane configurations for carbon capture from flue gas of power plants. Int. J. Greenh. Gas Control 86, 177–190. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijggc.2019.04.021" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijggc.2019.04.021&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[3] Arias, A.M., Mores, P.L., Scenna, N.J., Caballero, J.A., Mussati, S.F., Mussati, M.C., 2018. Optimal Design of a Two-Stage Membrane System for Hydrogen Separation in Refining Processes. Processes 6, 208. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/pr6110208" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.3390/pr6110208&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[4] Mores, P.L., Arias, A.M., Scenna, N.J., Caballero, J.A., Mussati, S.F., Mussati, M.C., 2018. Membrane-Based Processes: Optimization of Hydrogen Separation by Minimization of Power, Membrane Area, and Cost. Processes 6, 221. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/pr6110221" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.3390/pr6110221&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[5] Arias, A.M., Mussati, M.C., Mores, P.L., Scenna, N.J., Caballero, J.A., Mussati, S.F., 2016. Optimization of multi-stage membrane systems for CO2 capture from flue gas. Int. J. Greenh. Gas Control 53, 371–390. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijggc.2016.08.005" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijggc.2016.08.005&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[6] Arias, A.M., Mores, P.L., Scenna, N.J., Mussati, S.F., 2016. Optimal design and sensitivity analysis of post-combustion CO2 capture process by chemical aabsorption with amines. J. Clean. Prod. 115, 315–331. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2015.12.056" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jclepro.2015.12.056&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reinforcement Learning for PSE</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/reinforcement-learning/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/reinforcement-learning/</guid><description>&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/post/reinforcement-learning/featured_hu259738f748945f634c03d5b7c7684f95_59336_403144bc10074802df247030694e08bc.webp 400w,
/post/reinforcement-learning/featured_hu259738f748945f634c03d5b7c7684f95_59336_c79c23389733bca749875f8e1008fba8.webp 760w,
/post/reinforcement-learning/featured_hu259738f748945f634c03d5b7c7684f95_59336_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w"
src="https://optimalpse.github.io/post/reinforcement-learning/featured_hu259738f748945f634c03d5b7c7684f95_59336_403144bc10074802df247030694e08bc.webp"
width="760"
height="477"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/th>
&lt;th>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="" srcset="
/post/reinforcement-learning/pc_hud3c0e97c9a69add1fe991c938a75f802_147783_9272f12b9854dd2c1d3a1ed3143c65ac.webp 400w,
/post/reinforcement-learning/pc_hud3c0e97c9a69add1fe991c938a75f802_147783_1fd5a15bb7d1c2b6e9dc060dc5d83bb1.webp 760w,
/post/reinforcement-learning/pc_hud3c0e97c9a69add1fe991c938a75f802_147783_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://optimalpse.github.io/post/reinforcement-learning/pc_hud3c0e97c9a69add1fe991c938a75f802_147783_9272f12b9854dd2c1d3a1ed3143c65ac.webp"
width="760"
height="449"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;/table>
&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
The chemical industry requires efficient control systems to operate at the border of process constraints while optimizing for profit, safety, and sustainability. Reinforcement Learning (RL) is a control philosophy that aims to address the complex control problems present in chemical systems. RL utilises plant data to improve its control performance and has several advantages over other control strategies such as its offline inference time and flexibility to adapt to changing plant conditions. However, RL is an active area of research to develop and implement algorithms suitable for industrial useglobal optimum due to its inherent robustness.
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Safe Reinforcement Learning for Chemical Process Control</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/safe-rl-pc/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/safe-rl-pc/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Safe reinforcement learning (RL) in chemical process control is an emerging field that addresses the complexities and inherent risks of controlling chemical reactions and systems in real-time. This area of research focuses on designing AI-driven algorithms that can predict and mitigate potential model mismatches, ensuring operations' safety and stability.
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Sustainable Energy Systems</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/sus-energy-systems/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/post/sus-energy-systems/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
The design and optimization of sustainable energy systems represent a highly complex area of research, crucial for enhancing overall network efficiency and reliability. This field explores various strategies, including improving resource planning and load distribution across multiple sites, building operational resilience during outages and critical events, and boosting profitability through optimized utilization and reduced operational costs. Most significantly, these efforts are instrumental in reducing or eliminating the carbon footprint throughout the supply chain. To achieve these objectives, it is essential to transition from traditional single-objective optimization models to multi-objective pareto optimization, focusing on both profitability and decarbonization. Additionally, the integration of stochastic and robust optimization methods is critical for effectively managing system uncertainties such as market demand and supply.
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Discrete and mixed-variable experimental design with surrogate-based approach</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhu-discrete-2024/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhu-discrete-2024/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Human-Algorithm Collaborative Bayesian Optimization for Engineering Systems</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-human-algorithm-2024-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-human-algorithm-2024-1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>ARRTOC: Adversarially Robust Real-Time Optimization and Control</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/ahmed-arrtoc-2024/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/ahmed-arrtoc-2024/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Machine learning in process systems engineering: Challenges and opportunities</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/daoutidis-machine-2024/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/daoutidis-machine-2024/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Investigating the Reliability and Interpretability of Machine Learning Frameworks for Chemical Retrosynthesis</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/hastedt-investigating-2024/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/hastedt-investigating-2024/</guid><description/></item><item><title>PO-SRPP: A Decentralized Pivoting Path Planning Method for Self-Reconfigurable Satellites</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/ye-po-srpp-2024/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/ye-po-srpp-2024/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The automated discovery of kinetic rate models – methodological frameworks</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/servia-automated-2024/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/servia-automated-2024/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Expert-guided Bayesian Optimisation for Human-in-the-loop Experimental Design of Known Systems</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-expert-guided-2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-expert-guided-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Machine Learning and Hybrid Modelling for Reaction Engineering: Theory and Applications</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhang-machine-2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhang-machine-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Multi-fidelity data-driven design and analysis of reactor and tube simulations</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-multi-fidelity-2023/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-multi-fidelity-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Discovery of mixing characteristics for enhancing coiled reactor performance through a Bayesian optimisation-CFD approach</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/basha-discovery-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/basha-discovery-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Hierarchical planning-scheduling-control -- Optimality surrogates and derivative-free optimization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/van-de-berg-hierarchical-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/van-de-berg-hierarchical-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Machine Learning-Assisted Discovery of Novel Reactor Designs</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-machine-2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-machine-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>An Analysis of Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning for Decentralized Inventory Control Systems</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mousa-analysis-2023/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mousa-analysis-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>An efficient data-driven distributionally robust MPC leveraging linear programming</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-efficient-2023/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-efficient-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Design and planning of flexible mobile Micro-Grids using Deep Reinforcement Learning</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/caputo-design-2023/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/caputo-design-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Integrated experimental and photo-mechanistic modelling of biomass and optical density production of fast versus slow growing model cyanobacteria</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/cho-integrated-2023/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/cho-integrated-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Linearizing nonlinear dynamics using deep learning</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/ahmed-linearizing-2023/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/ahmed-linearizing-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A Hybrid Modelling Framework for Dynamic Modelling of Bioprocesses</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/wang-hybrid-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/wang-hybrid-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data-driven coordination of subproblems in enterprise-wide optimization under organizational considerations</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/van-de-berg-data-driven-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/van-de-berg-data-driven-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Distributional reinforcement learning for inventory management in multi-echelon supply chains</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/wu-2023100073/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/wu-2023100073/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Ensemble Kalman Filter for estimation of intracellular nucleotide sugars from extracellular metabolites in monoclonal antibodies</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/yu-ensemble-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/yu-ensemble-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Hybrid data-driven and first principles monitoring applied to the Tennessee Eastman process</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/iraola-hybrid-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/iraola-hybrid-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Investigating physics-informed neural networks for bioprocess hybrid model construction</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/rogers-investigating-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/rogers-investigating-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Neural ODEs as Feedback Policies for Nonlinear Optimal Control</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/sandoval-neural-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/sandoval-neural-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Online Feedback Optimization of Compressor Stations with Model Adaptation using Gaussian Process Regression</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zagorowska-online-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zagorowska-online-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Automated Discovery of Kinetic Rate Models -- Methodological Frameworks</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/servia-automated-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/servia-automated-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Tube-based distributionally robust model predictive control for nonlinear process systems via linearization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-2023108112/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-2023108112/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Tube-based distributionally robust model predictive control for nonlinear process systems via linearization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-tube-based-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-tube-based-2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A hybrid data-driven and mechanistic model soft sensor for estimating CO2 concentrations for a carbon capture pilot plant</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhuang-hybrid-2022/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhuang-hybrid-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Neural ODEs as Feedback Policies for Nonlinear Optimal Control</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/sandoval-neural-2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/sandoval-neural-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/contact/</guid><description/></item><item><title>People</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/people/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Deep Gaussian Process-based Multi-fidelity Bayesian Optimization for Simulated Chemical Reactors</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-deep-2022/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-deep-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Integrating process design and control using reinforcement learning</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/sachio-integrating-2022/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/sachio-integrating-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>An MIQP framework for metabolic pathways optimisation and dynamic flux analysis</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/gerken-starepravo-miqp-2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/gerken-starepravo-miqp-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Distributional Reinforcement Learning for Scheduling of Chemical Production Processes</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-distributional-2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-distributional-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A transfer learning approach for predictive modeling of bioprocesses using small data</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/rogers-transfer-2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/rogers-transfer-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A transfer learning approach for predictive modeling of bioprocesses using small data</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/rogers-transfer-2022-1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/rogers-transfer-2022-1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Chance Constrained Policy Optimization for Process Control and Optimization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/petsagkourakis-202235/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/petsagkourakis-202235/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Convex Q-learning: Reinforcement learning through convex programming</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/sitter-convex-2022/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/sitter-convex-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data-driven coordination of expensive black-boxes</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/van-de-berg-data-driven-2022/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/van-de-berg-data-driven-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data-driven optimization for process systems engineering applications</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/vandeberg-2022117135/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/vandeberg-2022117135/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Distributionally Robust MPC for Nonlinear Systems</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-2022606/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-2022606/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Industrial data science – a review of machine learning applications for chemical and process industries</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-industrial-2022-1/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-industrial-2022-1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Industrial data science–a review of machine learning applications for chemical and process industries</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-industrial-2022/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-industrial-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Piecewise Smooth Hybrid System Identification for Model Predictive Control</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/stolyarov-piecewise-2022/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/stolyarov-piecewise-2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Safe Real-Time Optimization using Multi-Fidelity Gaussian Processes</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/petsagkourakis-safe-2021/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/petsagkourakis-safe-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Constrained model-free reinforcement learning for process optimization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/pan-constrained-2021/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/pan-constrained-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Machine learning for biochemical engineering: A review</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-machine-2021/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-machine-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data-driven distributionally robust MPC using the Wasserstein metric</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-data-driven-2021/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-data-driven-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Quality by design modelling to support rapid RNA vaccine production against emerging infectious diseases</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/van-de-berg-quality-2021/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/van-de-berg-quality-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>An integrated dimensionality reduction and surrogate optimization approach for plant-wide chemical process operation</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/https-doi-org-10-1002-aic-17358/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/https-doi-org-10-1002-aic-17358/</guid><description/></item><item><title>An integrated dimensionality reduction and surrogate optimization approach for plant-wide chemical process operation</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-integrated-2021-1/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-integrated-2021-1/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data-driven distributionally robust MPC using the Wasserstein metric</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-2021-datadriven/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/zhong-2021-datadriven/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Machine learning for biochemical engineering: A review</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-2021108054/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/mowbray-2021108054/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Model-free safe reinforcement learning for chemical processes using Gaussian processes</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-2021504/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-2021504/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Synergising biomass growth kinetics and transport mechanisms to simulate light/dark cycle effects on photo-production systems</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/anye-cho-synergising-2021/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/anye-cho-synergising-2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>An adaptive data-driven modelling and optimization framework for complex chemical process design</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-202073/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-202073/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Constrained Reinforcement Learning for Dynamic Optimization under Uncertainty</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/petsagkourakis-202011264/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/petsagkourakis-202011264/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Superstructure Reaction Network Design for the Synthesis of Biobased Sustainable Nitrogen-Containing Polymers</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/doi-10-1021-acs-iecr-9-b-06511/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/doi-10-1021-acs-iecr-9-b-06511/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Surrogate Modelling and Optimization for Complex Liquefied Natural Gas Refrigeration Cycles</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-202011193/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/savage-202011193/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Reinforcement Learning for Batch-to-Batch Bioprocess Optimisation</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/petsagkourakis-2019919/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/publication/petsagkourakis-2019919/</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/admin/config.yml</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid><description/></item><item><title>Bayesian Optimization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/bayesian-optimization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/bayesian-optimization/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Data-Driven Optimization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/data-driven-optimization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/data-driven-optimization/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Deep Learning in Chemical Engineering</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/deep-learning-in-ce/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/deep-learning-in-ce/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Hybrid Modelling</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/hybrid-modelling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/hybrid-modelling/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Large Language Models</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/large-language-models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/large-language-models/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Process Control</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/process-control/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/process-control/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Reinforcement Learning</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/reinforcement-learning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/reinforcement-learning/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Statistical Learning</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/statistical-learning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/statistical-learning/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Supply Chain Optimization</title><link>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/supply-chain-optimization/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://optimalpse.github.io/research/supply-chain-optimization/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>