<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research | OptiML PSE</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/</link><atom:link href="https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Research</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/media/logo_hu5a76b0abcb7258b41069941c74c2d861_196285_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url><title>Research</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/</link></image><item><title>Large Language Models</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/large-language-models/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/large-language-models/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our research aims to advance large language models (LLMs) to serve as comprehensive scientific research assistants. We are investigating the current limitations of LLMs in tasks that require deep understanding and reasoning beyond textual data, such as interpreting tables and figures in scientific literature. To address these challenges, we are developing novel approaches to fine-tune pre-trained LLMs, enabling them to generate high-quality, research-focused outputs tailored to specific stages of the scientific process. Our goal is to create a multi-faceted research assistant that can provide specialized support throughout the research pipeline, from literature review and analysis to peer review and rebuttal, ultimately enhancing the efficiency and quality of scientific work.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bayesian Optimization</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/bayesian-optimization/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/bayesian-optimization/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Bayesian optimisation has been successfully applied in a number of complex domains including engineering systems where derivatives are often not available, such as those that involve simulation or propriety software. By removing the human from decision-making processes in favour of maximising statistical quantities such as expected improvement, complex functions can be optimised in an efficient number of samples. However, these engineering systems are often engaged with by domain experts such as engineers or chemists, and as such the behaviour of the underlying function cannot be considered completely unknown a-priori. Therefore, there exists significant scope to take advantage of the benefits of Bayesian optimisation in optimising expensive derivative-free problems, whilst enabling domain experts to inform the decision-making process, putting the human back into the loop.
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02852" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Link to publication.&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data-Driven Optimization</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/data-driven-optimization/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/data-driven-optimization/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Many engineering optimization problems can be described as "costly" black box problems, where the number of function evaluations is constrained. Engineers often create precise models of physical systems that are either differentiable or inexpensive to evaluate. These models can be solved efficiently, and their solutions can be applied to the actual system. However, when gradient information or cost-effective models are not available, it becomes necessary to use efficient optimization methods that rely solely on function evaluations - "data". These data-driven optimization algorithms are tailored to optimize functions without relying on explicit derivative information. The methods generally fall into two primary categories: model-based derivative-free methods, also referred to as surrogate-based optimization, and direct derivative-free methods. Model-based methods use information obtained through sampling the objective function to build, consult and update a model of the objective function during optimization. Direct methods navigate the optimization process based on sampled information only. Situated in-between these two categories are the finite-difference methods, which approximate derivatives using function evaluations.
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Hybrid Modelling</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/hybrid-modelling/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/hybrid-modelling/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hybrid Modelling is an emerging research area that combines the strengths of different modeling approaches, such as first-principles models and data-driven models, to create more accurate and robust representations of complex systems. Our research in this field focuses on developing novel methodologies and frameworks that can seamlessly integrate knowledge from different sources, such as physical laws, expert knowledge, and experimental data. By leveraging techniques such as Bayesian inference, transfer learning, and multiscale modeling, we aim to create hybrid models that can capture the underlying dynamics of complex systems across different scales and domains. Our work has applications in various fields, from chemical engineering to biotechnology, where accurate modeling is essential for design, optimization, and decision-making.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Process Control</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/process-control/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/process-control/</guid><description>&lt;p>Process Control is a vital research area that deals with the design and implementation of control strategies for industrial processes. The goal is to maintain process variables, such as temperature, pressure, and flow rate, within desired ranges to ensure product quality, safety, and efficiency. Our research focuses on developing advanced control algorithms that can handle the nonlinear and time-varying nature of industrial processes. By leveraging techniques such as model predictive control, adaptive control, and machine learning, we aim to create intelligent control systems that can autonomously adapt to changing process conditions and optimize performance in real-time.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reinforcement Learning</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/reinforcement-learning/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/reinforcement-learning/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Reinforcement Learning (RL) is a subfield of Artificial Intelligence (AI) which trains Machine Learning models to make optimal decisions. This is done in such a way that the model (or agent; or controller in a process engineering domain) learns how to take optimal actions as it explores the environment in which it resides.
RL has received a lot of attention, notable examples are ``machines" learning to play board games such as Go, or videogames such as DOTA 2 or Starcraft. Furthermore, game-playing is not all that RL is useful for. In previous work we have already optimized chemical processes under this same philosophy.
&lt;p>Reinforcement learning was designed to address the optimisation of stochastic dynamic systems. It so happens that in reality chemical processes are stochastic (due to process disturbances) and in many cases operated in dynamic mode. The difference with traditional RL applied in mainstream AI resides in the fact that RL is “data hungry” and does not consider constraints. This is a major drawback given that processes generally rely on much less data, while unbounded exploration (without constraints) can be dangerous or costly. This project aims to design a new RL algorithm that can be used to optimize complex chemical and biochemical processes which are still unresolved today.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Statistical Learning</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/statistical-learning/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/statistical-learning/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Statistical Learning is a rapidly growing field that combines the principles of statistics and machine learning to extract meaningful insights from data. Our research in this area focuses on developing novel algorithms and models that can handle the challenges posed by high-dimensional, noisy, and incomplete data. One of our primary areas of interest is Symbolic Regression, a powerful technique that aims to discover the underlying mathematical expressions that best describe the relationships within a given dataset.
&lt;p>Symbolic Regression goes beyond traditional regression methods by searching for the optimal combination of mathematical operators, variables, and constants that minimize the error between the model and the observed data. This approach allows for the discovery of interpretable and meaningful equations that can provide deep insights into the underlying physical or biological processes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Supply Chain Optimization</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/supply-chain-optimization/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/supply-chain-optimization/</guid><description>&lt;div style="text-align: justify">
Supply Chain Optimization is a critical area of research that focuses on improving the efficiency and effectiveness of supply chain operations. This involves the application of mathematical modeling, simulation, and optimization techniques to identify bottlenecks, reduce costs, and improve the overall performance of the supply chain network. Our research in this field aims to develop novel algorithms and frameworks that can handle the complexity and uncertainty inherent in modern supply chains. By leveraging advanced analytics and machine learning techniques, we seek to enable real-time decision-making and adaptive supply chain management.
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Deep Learning in Chemical Engineering</title><link>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/deep-learning-in-ce/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.optimlpse.co.uk/research/deep-learning-in-ce/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>